<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!-- This is an automatically generated file. -->
<Chapter Label="Chapter_Low-Level_Functions">
<Heading>Low-Level Functions</Heading>

<P/>
<Section Label="Chapter_Low-Level_Functions_Section_Low-Level_Functions">
<Heading>Low-Level Functions</Heading>

<P/>
<ManSection>
  <Func Arg="mat, options" Name="DoEchelonMatTransformationBlockwise" />
 <Returns>a record
</Returns>
 <Description>
This record contains
<List>
<Item>
vectors:
   the reduced row echelon form of the matrix mat without the zero rows
</Item>
<Item>
pivotrows and pivotcols:
   a list where the rows resp. columns with pivot elements are marked with 1
   whereas the other entries are 0
</Item>
<Item>
rank:
   the rank of the matrix mat
</Item>
<Item>
heads:
    list that contains at position i, if nonzero, the number of the row for
    that the pivot element is in column i.
</Item>
</List>
 and optionally
<List>
<Item>
coeffs:
   the transformation matrix needed to obtain the RREF from mat
</Item>
<Item>
relations:
   the kernel of the matrix mat if the underlying ring is a field
</Item>
<Item>
transformation:
   a transformation matrix needed to obtain the RREF from mat
   (filled with vectors that contain only zeros)
</Item>
</List>
<P/>
 Calculates the parallel Gauss algorithm. This is the version with the most
 options to specify the functionality. You can specify how the algorithm
 works and which return values it computes using the argument options which
 is a record that may contain the following fields:
<List>
<Item>
galoisField:
   the galois field of the matrix, e.g. GF(7)
</Item>
<Item>
numberBlocksHeight and numberBlocksWidth:
   The number of vertical and horizontal blocks in which to divide
   the matrix during the algorithm, note that you need to specify either none
   or both of those variables to make it work.
</Item>
<Item>
numberBlocks:
   Use this argument if you want the same number of vertical and horizontal chops.
</Item>
<Item>
withTrafo:
   A boolean specifying whether or not the transformation matrix is
   calculated, the default value is true.
</Item>
<Item>
isChopped: I don't know what this does!!! TODO
</Item>
<Item>
verify:
   A boolean specifying whether or not the result values should be directly
   checked, the default value is false.
</Item>
</List>
 </Description>
</ManSection>


</Section>


</Chapter>

